<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE collection SYSTEM "BioC.dtd"><collection><source>BioC-API</source><date>20260621</date><key>collection.key</key><document><id>31261512</id><passage><infon key="type">title</infon><offset>0</offset><text>A cross-sectional study of the ambulatory central artery stiffness index in patients with hypertension.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>104</offset><text>The present study aimed to investigate the characteristics of the ambulatory central artery stiffness index (AcASI) and its related factors. The association between AcASI and the left ventricular mass index (LVMI), and other factors related to atherosclerosis were explored.Patients with primary hypertension were enrolled into this study. Ambulatory central artery blood pressure (CABP) and ambulatory brachial artery blood pressure (BABP) were assessed using a Mobil-O-Graph NG hemomanometer, whereas AcASI and the ambulatory arterial stiffness index (AASI) were determined. LVMI was assessed by echocardiography.A total of 136 patients with primary hypertension were enrolled from May 2011 to January 2013 in Beijing Hospital. AcASI was significantly associated with AASI (r = 0.879, P &lt; .001). AcASI was significantly lower than AASI (0.422 ± 0.302 vs 0.482 ± 0.270; P &lt; .001). AcASI increased with age, ambulatory brachial mean blood pressure (MBP), and fasting glucose. AcASI was significantly associated with office pulse pressure (PP), ambulatory brachial PP, ambulatory central PP, and pulse wave velocity (PWV). AcASI, but not AASI, was significantly associated with LVMI. Receiver operator characteristic analysis indicated that AcASI and AASI could may be a predictor of left ventricular hypertrophy (LVH). Multiple regression analysis indicated that AcASI, chronic kidney disease, and hypertension course were associated with LVMI, but AASI was not.AcASI, which is obtained from ambulatory CABP monitoring, could be a new marker for the evaluation of atherosclerosis. AcASI may be stronger associated with LVH than AASI.</text></passage></document></collection>